Department of Women's Studies fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Department of Women's Studies fonds
1972 - 2004; predominant 1975 - 1991
F-63
88 cm of textual records 40 photographs 6 oversize posters
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of these records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the Government of Canada through Library and Archives Canada and the Canadian Council of Archives' National Archival Development Program (2008/2009).
Department of Gender, Sexuality, and Women's Studies
The Department of Women's Studies at SFU has its roots in the political climate on campus during the late 1960s and early 1970s. Some students and faculty expressed a desire to participate in research on women and the development of feminist theory. In the fall of 1971, the first course to focus on women—Geography 404: the Geography of Gender—was offered to 40 students. At the same time, SFU faculty members began to develop and participate in a series of non-credit courses relating to women's issues. As a result of the success of both Geography 404 and these non-credit courses, a proposal for a Women's Studies program was drafted. In 1975 this proposal was presented by Andrea Lebowitz and Margaret Benston to Senate and approved.
The Women's Studies program was established within the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, and offered its first course in 1976. The program was administered by the Women's Studies Coordinating Committee, which was responsible for hiring, course development, and other administrative details. The Coordinating Committee was composed of Women's Studies faculty members, elected student representatives, and associated faculty teaching in the program.
In 1985, when the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies was eliminated, the Women's Studies program was placed in the Faculty of Arts within the Department of Interdisciplinary Studies. Also in the 1980s, the Ruth Wynn Woodward Endowed Chair in Women's Studies was founded, a role that includes teaching, public speaking engagements, the organization of conferences, and the invitation of distinguished speakers. And, in 1985, the MA program was established and admitted its first students.
The 1990s brought further developments: the introduction of a certificate program in 1990; departmental status in 1991; the offering of joint majors, with English in 1991 and with Psychology in 1992; and the approval of Women's Studies as a major in 1994. Political Science and Sociology/Anthropology joint majors were added in 1997.
In 2000, the department introduced a course-based MA, followed by additional joint majors with Criminology, History, and Humanities in 2001. A PhD program was established in 2004, and a Gender Studies minor was added to the undergraduate program in the same year. By 2007-2008, there were 775 students enrolled in Women's Studies undergraduate programs and courses, with a further 23 students in the MA and PhD programs. As of 2008, there are six full-time faculty members, four faculty who are jointly appointed with another department, eight faculty from other departments who serve as associate members of the department, three professors emeritae, one adjunct faculty member, and one endowed professor. Three staff members are also employed by the department.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
The fonds consists of records relating to the activities of the department. Activities and events documented include the history of the department, the delivery of courses in Women's Studies, the administration of student work study programs and honorary degree nominations, and the organization of various events such as conferences, retreats, seminars and speakers series. Records include correspondence, reports, proposals, course outlines and descriptions, photographs, posters, conference materials, and other documents.
The material was arranged by the Archivist.
Benston, Maggie; Penfold, Sue; Silverman, Kaja; Kimball, Meredith; Lebowitz, Andrea; Strong-Boag, Veronica; Cohen, Marjorie Griffin; Stewart, Mary Lynn; Graphic materials; Photographic materials; Textual records
The records were transferred to Archives through the regular application of university Records Retention Schedules and Disposal Authorities (RRSDAs).
As of November 2008, all accessions have been processed. Further accruals are expected.
For other material relating to the Department of Women's Studies, see the finding aid to the Department of Women's Studies Collection, F-62.
Access to some files may be restricted in accordance with the provisions of British Columbia's Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (RSBC 1996 c. 165). Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File list is available.
- Department history and structure files, 1975 - 1983; F-63-1; 13 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the evolution of the department, in particular the establishment of the Women's Studies Program at SFU and the introduction of a Master of Arts degree in Women's Studies. Records include correspondence, reports, and proposals.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist.
  Further accruals are expected.
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  A file list is available.
  - Academic Planning Committee report - Women's Studies program, 1975; F-63-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Women's Studies - faculty authorizations, 1975 - 1979; F-63-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
    Pending review
  - Graduate proposal - letters of enquiry (availability), 1980 - 1981; F-63-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
    Restricted in whole
  - Graduate proposal - SCAP submission, 1981; F-63-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
  - Graduate proposal - Women's Studies, 1981; F-63-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
  - Graduate Program proposal - Women's Studies, 1981; F-63-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
  - Graduate proposal - letters of support, 1981; F-63-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
  - Graduate proposal - Assessment Committee - reply, 1982; F-63-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
  - Graduate proposal - general correspondence, 1983; F-63-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
  - Graduate proposal - U.C.B.C. reply, 1983; F-63-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 63-1)
- Course files, 1976 - 1990; F-63-2; 37 cm of textual records; General note: Course numbers in file titles are based on original supplied titles, which are also reflected on course outline sheets. Some course numbers appear to have been used for more than one course. For example, course number WS 302-3 has been variously known as "Women and religion," "Women and the law," and "Women and film," in different semesters.
  Series consists of records documenting the content and evaluation standards of courses. Records include course outlines and descriptions, reading lists, class schedules, examination and assignment questions, and other documents.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Course files were originally housed by the creator in individual folders by course number and semester. Records are now housed in individual folders by course number, and grouped within by semester.
  Further accruals to the series are expected.
  - WS 001-3 -- Issues in Women's Health and Health Care, 1978 - 1982; F-63-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 63-2)
  - WS 001-3 -- Issues in Women's Health and Health Care, 1983; F-63-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 63-2)
  - WS 100-3 -- Introduction to Women's Studies, 1976 - 1981; F-63-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 63-2)
  - WS 100-3 -- Introduction to Women's Studies, 1982 - 1984; F-63-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 63-2)
  - WS 100-4 -- Introduction to Women's Studies, 1985 - 1986; F-63-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 63-2)
  - WS 200-3 -- Women's Roles - A Comparative Study, 1976 - 1984; F-63-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 63-2)
  - WS 201-3 -- Women in Canada 1600-1920, 1977 - 1985; F-63-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 63-2)
  - WS 202-3 -- Women in Canada 1920-present, 1976 - 1985; F-63-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 203-3 -- Female Roles in Contemporary Society, 1976 - 1986; F-63-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 204-3 -- Women, Science and Technology, 1984 - 1986; F-63-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 205-3 -- Women and Popular Culture, 1984 - 1986; F-63-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 300-5 -- Feminist Theory, 1978 - 1986; F-63-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 301-3 -- Special topics, 1978 - 1986; F-63-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 302-3 -- Women and Religion, 1980 - 1985; F-63-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 303-3 -- Women and The Law, 1980 - 1986; F-63-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 310-5 -- Women and The Law, 1982 - 1984; F-63-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 400-5 -- Advanced Methodology, 1976 - 1986; F-63-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 401-5, 402-5, 403-5 -- Research Projects, 1983 - 1986; F-63-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 63-3)
  - WS 001-3 -- Issues in women’s health and health care, 1989 - 1990; F-63-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 100-4 -- Perspectives on women: introduction to women's studies, 1988 - 1989; F-63-2-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 201-3 -- Women in Canada: 1600-1920, 1988 - 1989; F-63-2-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 202-3 -- Women in Canada: 1920 to the present, 1989; F-63-2-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 203-3 -- Female roles in contemporary society, 1988 - 1989; F-63-2-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 204-3 -- Women, science and technology, 1989; F-63-2-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 205-3 -- Women and popular culture, 1988; F-63-2-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 300-5/821-5 -- Voices from the silence: feminist psychoanalytic psychotherapy with women, 1988; F-63-2-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 300-5 -- Women and film: films and theories, 1989; F-63-2-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 300 -- Women and music, 1988; F-63-2-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 301-3 -- Women and the media, 1989; F-63-2-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 301-3 -- Women and dance, 1989; F-63-2-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 302-3 -- Women and the law, 1988; F-63-2-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 302-3 -- Women and film, 1988 - 1989; F-63-2-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 302-3/824-5 -- Canadian women and economic policy, 1989; F-63-2-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 303-3 -- Women and religion, 1988 - 1989; F-63-2-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 303-3/823-5 -- Women’s writing in Canada and feminist theory, 1989; F-63-2-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 303-3 -- Women and contemporary Canadian literature, 1989; F-63-2-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 400-5/800-5 -- Advanced women’s studies, 1988 - 1989; F-63-2-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
  - WS 401-5, 402-2, 403-3 -- Reading/research project, 1988 - 1989; F-63-2-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 63-4)
    Restrict in whole
- Administrative files, 1978 - 1988; F-63-3; 10 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to various administrative activities carried out by the department, including work study programs for students and an honorary degree nomination (Muriel Duckworth). Records include correspondence, proposals, and nomination documentation such as CVs, articles, and other background documentation.
  The series was established by the archivist to bring together materials of an administrative nature, including the carrying out of student work study programs and honorary degree nominations.
  Duckworth, Muriel
  - Work study (modified) program, 1983 - 1984; F-63-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Work study program, 1984 - 1985; F-63-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Work study program, 1986; F-63-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Work study program, 1986 - 1987; F-63-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Work study program, 1987 - 1988; F-63-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Youth employment program, 1978 - 1983; F-63-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Challenge '85 -- BC/Canada Summer Employment Program, 1985; F-63-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Challenge '86 -- BC/Canada Summer Employment Program, 1986; F-63-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Challenge '87 -- BC/Canada Summer Employment Program, 1987; F-63-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Challenge '88 -- BC/Canada Summer Employment Program, 1988; F-63-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 63-5)
  - Muriel Duckworth -- Honorary degree nomination, 1985 - 1986; F-63-3-0-0-11; General note: SFU conferred an honorary degree on Muriel Duckworth in 1986. (Archival box - standard 63-5)
- Conferences, seminars and retreats files, 1987 - 1990; F-63-4; 23 cm of textual records 39 photographs; Physical description: 13 photographs located in F-63-4-1-0-1 Physical description: 26 photographs located in F-63-4-3-0-3
  Series consists of records documenting various conferences, seminars, and retreats organized by the department, and in particular those sponsored by the Ruth Wynn Woodward Endowed Chair. See sub-series descriptions for activities documented and record types included.
  The series was established by the archivist to bring together all textual materials relating to the various conferences, seminars, and retreats organized by the department.
  - General files, 1990; F-63-4-1; 13 photographs
    Sub-series consists of one file relating to a retreat that took place in April 1990. Records include photographs.
    The sub-series was established by the archivist to bring together all records of a general nature relating to conferences, seminars and retreats, including single files pertaining to specific events.
    - Bowen Island retreat, women's studies, April 21, 1990 (photographs), F-63-4-1-0-1 (Archival box - small 63-8)
      Photographic materials
  - Telling It: Women and Language Across Cultures conference files, 1988 - 1989; F-63-4-2; 8 cm of textual records; General note: The research assistant for the conference was Jill Stainsby, who worked on the bibliography project and took notes at the conference. For material relating to Stainsby, see F-66, Gillian Stainsby fonds.
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the "Telling It: Women and Language Across Cultures" conference held by the department on 25 and 26 November 1988 at the downtown SFU campus. Speakers at the conference included Jeannette Armstrong, Barbara Herringer, Surjeet Kalsey, Joy Kogawa, Sky Lee, Lee Maracle, Louise Profeit-LeBlanc, and Betsy Warland. There was also a performance by Vancouver Sath. Records include registration and speaker lists, correspondence, grant proposals, promotional materials, evaluations, documentation relating to a bibliography, a final budget, and other documents.
    The sub-series was established by the archivist in order to maintain the original grouping of multiple files created by the department for the "Telling It" conference.
    Lee, Sky; Maracle, Lee; Warland, Betsy; Armstrong, Jeannette; Herringer, Barbara; Kogawa, Joy; Profeit-LeBlanc, Louise; Vancouver Sath; Kalsey, Surjeet
    No further accruals are expected.
    For other material relating to the conference, see:
    Telling It Book Collective: Sky Lee et al. "Telling It: Women and Language Across Cultures, the Transformation of a Conference." Vancouver, BC: Press Gang Publishers, 1990.
    Three copies of this title are held by SFU libraries (call number PR 9035 T44 1990). The book includes all but one of the transcribed presentations of the conference speakers.
    For editorial correspondence, production, promotion, and review files relating to the book, see F-184, Press Gang Publishers fonds.
    - Telling It: Women and Language Across Cultures conference (Nov. 1988) -- speakers, publishers, registration, 1988 - 1989; F-63-4-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 63-6)
      Open with enclosures
      Access review (Nov 22, 2022) – The bulk of the file is open. However, it includes a small number of documents (3) that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (personal contact information, social insurance number). Restricted documents have been removed (enclosed); the rest of the file is open. Enclosed records may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
    - Telling It: Women and Language Across Cultures conference (Nov. 1988) -- grants, on-site arrangments, 1988 - 1989; F-63-4-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 63-6)
      Open, no restrictions
      Access review (Nov 24, 2022) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
    - Telling It: Women and Language Across Cultures conference (Nov. 1988) -- ads, flyer, brochure, evaluations, program package, F-63-4-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 63-6)
      Access review (Nov 23, 2022) – The bulk of the file is open. However, it includes a small number of documents (2) that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (individual’s own views or opinions). Restricted documents have been removed (enclosed); the rest of the file is open. Enclosed records may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
    - Telling It: Women and Language Across Cultures conference (Nov. 1988) -- bibliography, proceedings notes, vol. 1, 1988 - 1989; F-63-4-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 63-6)
      Open, reading room
      Access review (Nov 22, 2022) – File includes records that contain some individuals' personal contact informat. File can be accessed in the Archives' reading room, but documents containing contact information cannot be photographed and will be redacted in any digital access copies made by Archives.
    - Telling It: Women and Language Across Cultures conference (Nov. 1988) -- bibliography, proceedings notes, vol. 2, 1988 - 1989; F-63-4-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 63-6)
    - Telling It: Women and Language Across Cultures conference (Nov. 1988) -- budget, 1989; F-63-4-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 63-6)
      Access review (Nov 23, 2022) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - The Female Constituency seminar files, 1987 - 1988; F-63-4-3; 9 cm of textual records 26 photographs
    Sub-series consists of records relating to "The Female Constituency" seminar held by the department on 6 February 1988 at SFU's Burnaby campus. Speakers included Rosemary Brown (1987 Ruth Wynn Woodward Professor), Marilyn Callahan, Penny Coates, Reva Dexter, Ruth Emery, Ellen Gee, Clarissa Green, Elaine Jacobson, Helga Jacobson, Arlene Tigar McLaren, Barbara Whittington, and Lillian Zimmerman. Records include correspondence, participant and invitation lists, a grant proposal, promotional and program package materials, a bibliography (which was offered for purchase post-conference), budget documentation, photographs, and other documents.
    The sub-series was established by the archivist in order to maintain the original grouping of multiple files created by the department for "The Female Constituency" seminar.
    Coates, Penny; Gee, Ellen M.; Callahan, Marilyn; Dexter, Reva; Emery, Ruth; Green, Clarissa; Jacobson, Elaine; Jacobson, Helga; McLaren, Arlene Tigar; Whittington, Barbara; Zimmerman, Lillian; Brown, Rosemary
    - The Female Constituency seminar (Feb. 1988), vol. 1, 1987 - 1988; F-63-4-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 63-6)
    - The Female Constituency seminar (Feb. 1988), vol. 2, 1987 - 1988; F-63-4-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 63-6)
    - The Female Constituency seminar (Feb. 1988) (photographs), vol. 3, 1987 - 1988; F-63-4-3-0-3 (Archival box - small 63-8)
    - The Female Constituency seminar (Feb. 1988) -- bibliography, F-63-4-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 63-6)
    - The Female Constituency seminar (Feb. 1988) -- program package, F-63-4-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 63-7)
    - The Female Constituency seminar (Feb. 1988) -- speech by Reva Dexter, F-63-4-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 63-7)
    - RWWP Conference, Female Constituency (Feb. 1988) -- budget, grant, money, 1987 - 1988; F-63-4-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 63-7)
  - BC and Yukon retreat files, 1987 - 1988; F-63-4-4; 3 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to a retreat held by the department May 13 through 15, 1988 at Bowen Island. The retreat was for women's studies instructors from colleges and universities in BC and the Yukon. Talks were given by Maggie Benston, Lynda Erickson, Daphne Marlatt, and Greta Nemiroff. Records include correspondence, participant and invitation lists, program package and reference materials, a final budget, and other documents.
    The sub-series was established by the archivist in order to maintain the original grouping of multiple files created by the department for the BC and Yukon retreat.
    Nemiroff, Greta; Erickson, Lynda; Benston, Maggie; Marlatt, Daphne
    - BC and Yukon retreat (May 1988) -- general, 1987 - 1988; F-63-4-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 63-7)
    - BC and Yukon retreat (May 1988) -- budget, F-63-4-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 63-7)
    - BC and Yukon retreat (May 1988) -- reference material, F-63-4-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 63-7)
- Speakers and lectures files, 1977 - 1991; F-63-5; 9 cm of textual records 1 photograph 1 oversize poster; Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-63-5-0-0-7 Physical description:
  Series consists of records documenting various lectures and talks given by high-profile, invited speakers, including those sponsored by the Ruth Wynn Woodward Endowed Chair. Speakers have included Lorenne M.G. Clark, Linda M. Fedigan, Ruth Hubbard, Evelyn Fox Keller, Jane Rule, and Eleanor Wachtel, among others. Records include correspondence, proposals, CVs, promotional materials (including posters), and other documentation.
  The series was established by the archivist to bring together all records relating to the various speakers and lectures organized by the department.
  Keller, Evelyn Fox; Fedigan, Linda M.; Rule, Jane; Hubbard, Ruth; Clark, Lorenne M.G.; Wachtel, Eleanor
  - Ruth Wynn Woodward endowed chair -- Distinguished Visitors, 1988 - 1991; F-63-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 63-7)
    Restricted in part
  - Lecture series -- Women and theatre arts; Occupational health and safety for clerical workers (Fall 1986/Spring 1987), 1986 - 1987; F-63-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 63-7)
  - Lecture series -- Women, medicine and psychoanalysis (Spring 1986), vol. 1, vol. 1, 1985 - 1986; F-63-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 63-7)
  - Lecture series -- Women, medicine and psychoanalysis (Spring 1986) (oversize poster), vol. 2, 1985 - 1986; F-63-5-0-0-4
  - Programs of Distinction -- Lectures by distinguished visitors, vol. 1, 1977 - 1984; F-63-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 63-7)